Transport Workers Union of America Local 2001 Files 5800
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Transport Workers Union of America Local 2001 Files
1937-1979
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Transport Workers Union of America (TWUA)
5800
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Case files, records (documents).
This collection consists of the records of Salvatore S. Biondo, executive vice-president and president of TWU Local 2001, Railroad Division, in Albany, New York.
3125304
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, September 1, 2017
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, September 1, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Transport Workers Union of America [TWU] was founded by New York City subway workers in 1934, and then expanded to represent other transit employees across the United States. Their largest Local is Local 100, whose membership consists of New York City's mass transit workers. TWU also represents flight attendants, grounds crew, and maintenance workers for a number of airlines as well as employees of Amtrak, ConRail, and a few short line railroads.
The TWU was one of the first unions to join the Congress of Industrial Organizations [CIO], and was known for its left-leaning politics. One of TWU's founders and its first president, Mike Quill, was a close ally of the Communist Party USA before renouncing all ties in 1948. The TWU was also unique among railroad and transit unions in that it fostered close ties with the African-American community and the NAACP, included quotas for the hiring of African-Americans in its collective bargaining agreements, and supported a strong civil rights platform which advocated for a national platform to combat racism as well as combating the racism found among its own members.
TWU started representing railway employees in 1954 when the United Railroad Workers of America [URRWA] on the Pennsylvania Railroad [PRR] voted to join the TWU. The URRWA was itself an outgrowth of the CIO's United Railway Organizing Committee, which was chartered in 1941 to organize non-operating employees on the railways. The Committee organized many different non-operating crafts, including carmen, car inspectors, food service workers, maintenance of way, and maintenance of equipment employees. Like the TWU, the URRWA was committed to strong union ideals, promoting racial equality, fighting discrimination, and serving as a counterpoint to the railroad brotherhoods of the AFL. The URRWA represented around 40,000 employees of the Pennsylvania Railroad; in order to increase their negotiating power, the Committee voted to affiliate with the TWU, thus forming the Railroad Division of the TWU.
In 1955, TWU Local 2001 was chartered to represent the members on the PRR, which included the employees of the PRR owned Hudson and Manhattan Railroad. During the mergers among carriers that occurred over the next few decades, TWU Local 2001 came to represent employees on the PATH system, formerly the Hudson and Manhattan; employees on the PennCentral, comprised of the PRR, the New York Central, and the New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad; and the successors to the PennCentral, Amtrak and Conrail as well as New Jersey Transit and MetroNorth.
Currently, TWU Local 2001 represents roughly 1,600 railroaders on seven different railroads in four states: Pennsylvania, New Jersey, New York, and Connecticut.
For more information, see History TWU Local 2001 http://local2001.twu.org/history/
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1937-1979
Bulk dates: 1969-1979
This collection contains the files of Salvatore S. Biondi, vice-president and president of TWU Local 2001 in Albany, New York. His files are primarily concerned with the carmen who worked in the Selkirk Yard. His files regarding union members, including grievances, claims, investigations, and personnel files, are restricted.
Also found in this collection is extensive documentation of the merger between the New York Central and Pennsylvania Railroad into the Penn Central Transportation Company and the effect it had on the employees of the carriers. It also includes extensive documentation of the further effects the Penn Central bankruptcy and the formation of ConRail and Amtrak had on these same employees.
Also found in this collection is extensive correspondence with the Railroad Division of the TWU in Long Island City, New York.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials. Files regarding union members, including grievances, claims, investigations, and personnel files, are restricted.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3007: Maurice Neufeld Papers /4073: James O. Morris Office Files /4095: Alice Grant Additional Records /4212: Kheel Center Current Documents Correspondence /4280 P: ILR School Ives Hallway Portrait Gallery Photographs 5012: Saul Wallen Papers 5024: Theodore W. Kheel Arbitration Awards 5051: U.S. Emergency Board No. 125 Records 5085: U.S. National Mediation Board Transcripts Regarding American Air Lines and Transport Workers Union of America 5102: Emergency Board No. 129, Long Island Railroad and the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Locals 517 and 1090, Records 5114: New York City Transit Authority Fact Finding Panel Records 5118: New York City Board of Transportation and the Transport Workers Union Records 5129: Maxwell Copelof Arbitration Briefs, Exhibits, Transcripts and Decisions 5131: Sidney A. Wolff Arbitration Files 5140: NYS PERB Agreements 5206: Local 1199 Records 5275: AFL-CIO Internal Disputes Plan Decisions of the Impartial Umpire 5305: Benjamin H. Wolf Papers 5477: Benjamin Wolf Papers 5488 A: BRAC Chicago Files 5488 B: BRAC Records 5511: Benjamin Wolf Additional Papers 5538: James C. Hill Arbitration Files 5539: Benjamin H. Wolf Additional Arbitration Files 5541: Philip Taft Papers 5548: I. Robert Feinberg Arbitration Records 5549: Edwin S. Smith Papers 5576: S. Stanley Alderfer Arbitration Files 5581: New York State Board of Mediation Cases 5582: Archives Foreign File (AFF) 5587: John Horlacher Arbitration Records 5588: David L. Cole Papers 5609: Philip Ross Collection of NLRB Documents 5619: ACWA Records 5678: Gabriel Alexander Additional Arbitration Files 5712: Burton B. Turkus Arbitration Files 5728: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5733: Peter Seitz Arbitration Files 5735: BRAC Additional Records 5776 AV: Theodore W. Kheel Interviews and Programs 5780/002: ILGWU David Dubinsky Correspondence 5780/014: ILGWU Local 22, Charles S. Zimmerman Papers 5780/203: ILGWU Jay Mazur Papers 5802: Louis Yagoda Arbitration files 5803: Benjamin Wolf Additional Arbitration Files 5831 mf: The CIO Files of John L. Lewis, Pt. II: CIO General Files on Microfilm 5863 mf: Department of Justice Investigative Files on Industrial Workers of the World, Part 1 on Microfilm 5888: Emanuel Stein Papers 5935: Jacob Seidenberg Additional Arbitration Files 5956: Archives Organization File Additional records 5956: Archives Organization File Additional records 5990 mf: Transport Workers Union of America Minutes on Microfilm 6017: Theodore W. Kheel Newspaper Clipping File 6021 MB: Theodore W. Kheel Memorabilia 6021: Theodore W. Kheel Records 6021/003: Theodore W. Kheel Arbitration files 6021/004: Theodore W. Kheel Legal Files 6021/005: Theodore W. Kheel Speeches and Articles 6021/006: Theodore W. Kheel Non-Profit Organization Files 6021/007: Theodore W. Kheel Subject Files 6021/010: Theodore W. Kheel Additional Files 6030: Archival Collective Bargaining Agreements File 6034: Rare Pamphlet Collection 6035: Constitution Collection 6046: Archives Union File (AUF) 6059 OH: Thomas Shactman Interviews with Theodore W. Kheel 6091: Marcia Greenbaum Papers 6173: NYS PERB Harold Newman Files 6178/003: BLS Collection of Collective Bargaining Agreements (Part 3) 6178/008: BLS Collection of Collective Bargaining Agreements (Part 8) 6178/010: BLS Collection of Collective Bargaining Agreements (Part 10) 6178/018: BLS Collection of Collective Bargaining Agreements (Part 18) 6178/019: BLS Collection of Collective Bargaining Agreements (Part 19) 6178/022 mf: BLS Collection of Collective Bargaining Agreements (Part 22) on Microfilm 6190: Jacob J. Kaufman Papers 6194 OH: College of Labor and Employment Lawyers Interview with Theodore W. Kheel 6196 OH: New York City Central Labor Council Interview of Theodore W. Kheel for Central Archives 6206: Clyde Summers Office Files 6275: Tia Schneider Denenberg Arbitration Files 6300 MB: Steven Singer Labor Collection Memorabilia 6305: William B. Wolf Papers 6305 AV: William B. Wolf Audio-Visual 6305 P: William B. Wolf Photographs 6374 PUBS: Archives Union Files (AUF) Part 2 6382 AV(d): Theodore W. Kheel Memorial Service Audio-Visual Materials (digital) 6429: David L. Cole Collections 6433: Benjamin H. Wolf Collections 6438: William B. Wolf Collections
Railroads -- New York (State); Transport workers -- Labor unions -- United States -- Sources; Collective labor agreements -- Railroads -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Railroads -- Mergers -- United States; Biondo, Salvatore S.; Transport Workers Union of America.; Transport Workers Union of America -- Local 2001 (Albany, NY); Penn Central Transportation Company; New York Central Railroad; Pennsylvania Railroad; Brotherhood of railway Carmen of America, AFL-CIO; Amtrak; Conrail
3125304
- Claims filed by TWU with Penn Central Transportation Co., 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Claims file on behalf of employees at Selkirk Departure yard.
- Correspondence from TWU Railroad Division, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence from Penn Central Transportation Co. re filed claims, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Amtrak Investigations of Employees At Selkirk Departure yard, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Restricted
- ConRail: Reorganization and Title V, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Rensselaer Maintenance Facility, Seniority Rosters, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- General Correspondence, 1951-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Notice of Investigation, Trial, or Hearing, 1968-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence from Penn Central Transportation Co. re filed claims, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence from Amtrak re facilities at Albany-Rensselaer, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- TWU Local 2001 General Outgoing Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Weekly Reports, S.S. Biondo, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Weekly Reports, S.S. Biondo, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Weekly Reports, S.S. Biondo, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Weekly Reports, S.S. Biondo, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Weekly Reports, S.S. Biondo, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Deposit Slips, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Personnel file, Discipline: RB, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Personnel file, Discipline: FA, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Personnel file, Discipline: FA, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Personnel file, Discipline: CWA, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Personnel file, Discipline: RAH, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Personnel file, Discipline: JS, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Personnel file, Discipline: DR, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Correspondence re Furloughs, Seniority Roster, and Safety Conditions, 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  At Selkirk Yard, Albany-Rensselaer
- Discipline: Absenteeism and Sick Leave, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Railroad Docket 15887 and 15888, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Information, Rules, and Wages in Selkirk Yard, 1963-1974 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Correspondence, bulletins, and pamphlets
- Dismissals and Employee Counseling Service, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Docketed Claims, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Wage and Benefit Agreements, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Transport Workers Union of America General Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Conrail Memorandums, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Re Bulletin Board postings
- ConRail Rosters, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Minutes of Disciplinary Hearing [folder 1 of 2], 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 35a)
- Minutes of Disciplinary Hearing [folder 2 of 2], 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 35b)
- Sickness/Medical Benefits, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Wage Increase and General Agreements, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Personnel file, Discipline: RC, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 38a)
- Northeastern Area bulletins, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 38b)
- AFL-CIO Platform Proposals (1976) and article re Senate Appointments (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Apprentice Training, 1945-1956 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Claim filed against NY Central, 1959-1965 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- West Albany Trainmasters Investigation, Part 1, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- West Albany Investigation, Part 2, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Transportation Investigation, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Railroad Docket 14116 re operation of Wreck Crane, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Claims filed: FH and MDE, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Personnel file, Discipline: SB, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- NY Central System mergers, 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Agreements in Effect: merger protection for employees, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Emergency Board #187 Report, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- National Mediation Board: Pittsburgh and Lake Erie Railroad v. AFL-CIO, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Year 1970: notes from TWU Negotiating committee meeting [folder 1 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 8a)
- Year 1970: notes from TWU Negotiating committee meeting [folder 2 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 8b)
- Protection for Employees in Merger of NY Central and Penn RR, 1964-1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  New Implementing Agreement in Effect May 31, 1970
- Agreements between Bankruptcy Trustees of Penn RR and their Employees, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Nat'l railroad Adjustment Board, Second Division: Decisions, 1951-1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  In re Brotherhood of Railway Carmen of America [BRCMA]
- Memorandum of Agreement re Transfer of Work, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Supplement Railroad Agreements re merger of Penn RR and NY Central, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Dispute re Selkirk Departure Yard "Roll-By" Inspections, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  TWU Local 2001 vs. Penn Central
- State of NY Industrial Code, Public Hearing Draft #1, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Agreement between AMTRAK and Its Employees, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Annotated draft of agreement
- Pass Instructions, 1968-1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  For employees
- Amtrak: Interim Agreement and Appendix C-2, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Drafts and negotiations
- National Agreement between TWU, BRCMA, and ConRail, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Conrail: Work Rule Agreement, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Effective September 1, 1977
- Changes in Green Book Agreement, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  As a result of new Work Rule Agreement with ConRail
- Merger and Implementing Agreement and Supplementing Agreements, 1970-1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Vacation Agreement Covering Non-Operating Employees, 1942-1964 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Question and Answer sheets
- Speeches and News/Press Releases re railroading, 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Amtrak Agreement with Appendices, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Amtrak No. 23 Arbitration: Southwest District and United Transportation Union, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Claims re Extra Men in Work Service, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Conrail: Investigations, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Absenteeism Letters, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Notices of Investigation, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- ConRail: October 1978 Agreement (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Employee Claims, 1969-1978 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Investigation Transcripts (Partial), 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Safety-Related Pamphlets, 1956-1974 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Manuals/Instructions, 1956-1971 (Box 2, Folder 35a)
- Constitutions and Agreements (1 of 2), 1951-1977 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Constitutions and Agreements (2 of 2), 1954-1977 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Insurance and Benefit Plans, 1937-1977 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- TWU and BRCMA Pamphlets, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 39)